Finding Aid for Luther H. Buchele papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Luther H. Buchele papers 1935-2008, 1950-1970
Buchele, Luther H., 1920-
3 linear feet
2013165 Aa 2
Papers of Luther H. Buchele, first general manager of the Inter-Cooperative Council (ICC), the governing body of student cooperatives in Ann Arbor, Mich., who served the ICC for 34 years. Collection includes Buchele's personal and professional correspondence and biographical material. Material related to national and regional student cooperative organizations, as well as the cooperative movement, includes surveys, reports, conference material and publications. Also included material related to Buchele's political activism and interests.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Joan Allison Buchele (donor no. 5052 ) in July 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Raised during the Great Depression in Cedar Vale in southeastern rural Kansas, Buchele was first exposed to farming cooperatives and saw them as a way for people to work together to overcome financial difficulties. Buchele's father died in 1932 when Luther was in 5th grade. There were seven boys in Buchele family and they learned cooperation by doing farm chores and helping their mother to save the mortgaged farm. Early on cooperatives were a big part of Buchele's life, for he shopped at the co-ops, delivered grain to the elevators, herded livestock to the shipping yards, and attended the various co-ops' annual meetings with members of his family. As a Cedar Vale High School junior in 1937, he won a cooperative marketing contest sponsored by the Kansas 4-H clubs. He won a trip to a five-day cooperative marketing camp at 4-H Encampment Building on the state fairgrounds in Hutchinson, Kansas. There he met the leaders of the Consumer Cooperative Association (CCA, later Farmland Cooperatives).
When he enrolled at the University of Kansas in Lawrence in 1939, Buchele joined the newly organized Jayhawk co-op which offered the only integrated housing on campus. Buchele received his A.B. in Zoology in 1946 and M.A. in Bacteriology in 1948. Starting in 1946 he worked on a Bacteriological warfare project under Dr. Cora Downs at the University of Kansas on tularemia (rabbit fever) and used part of the material for his Master's thesis, "The Pathogenesis of Bacterium Tularense." The war project was to experiment with Tulerense to see if mass populations could be infected by spraying the germ over troops in the field, stadiums or theaters. Buchele also taught microbiology for the period of 2 years.
At the University he helped organize the Student Housing Association, the Central League of Campus Cooperatives (CLCC), and six additional student co-ops. He helped to establish the North American Student Cooperative League (NASCL), in 1946 and served for two years as its executive secretary. In 1949 Buchele accepted a part-time job as the Executive Secretary of the NASCL, working out of a clothes closet in Don Henry Co-op at the University of Kansas. He also was twice elected president of the University of Kansas YMCA. In 1950 he ran as a Democrat for 3rd Ward Councilman in Lawrence.
In Spring 1951 the Inter-Cooperative Council (ICC) in Ann Arbor advertised in Co-ops on Campus that it needed an Executive Secretary. Buchele applied and was hired in September 1951. He later became the ICC's General Manager. When he took the job, he lived in Nakamura House, then one of five co-ops on campus.
In 1968 the North American Student Cooperative Organization (NASCO) was formed. NASCO grew out of a conference promoting loans for student co-op houses from the U.S. Department of Urban Development. The University of Michigan Government Council granted NASCO an office down the hall from the ICC on the fourth floor of the Michigan Union. Buchele was asked to advise new NASCO staff members on many matters. As Buchele noted in his autobiographical writing, having NASCO Office so nearby made the ICC a more vital organization on campus.
Buchele, worked with more than 15,000 residents over his 34 years at the ICC. At the start of each school year, Buchele brought new dishes and silverware to each house, a visit he used as an opportunity to meet students and encourage members to have pride in their houses. He served as a liaison between co-op members and University of Michigan administrators who were often at odds with the co-ops during the fifties and sixties. For a number of years Buchele recruited the University of Michigan students to help edit NASCL magazine and plan yearly nation-wide conferences.
In the 1960s, Buchele successfully argued to the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development that cooperative housing qualified as affordable housing. As a result the ICC was able to secure a million-dollar, low-interest loan to build the North Campus co-op houses was opened in 1970. A tireless advocate for students, Buchele also convinced legislators that co-op members, who don't rent their rooms, but rather own a share of the house, should qualify for a renter's tax credit.
Buchele is hailed by many as the 'father of the student cooperative movement' because the cooperatives he built served as models for those at other universities. He served as a coach and trainer for generations of college cooperators, many of who have become leaders in today's cooperatives. Even after retirement Buchele was a fixture at the ICC's Winter Annual Meeting for many years. One of the ICC houses, located at 1510 Hill Street, is named after Luther Buchele. In 1987 Buchele was inducted into the Cooperative Hall of Fame of the National Cooperative Business Association in Washington, D.C., and in 1991 he was nominated to the NASCO Hall of Fame. He was also recognized as a "Cooperative Pioneer" by the Michigan Association of Cooperatives.
Luther Buchele married Joan Alison Bross in February 1961. They had four children: Royd Stefan, Theresa Allison, Libbie Ann, and Heidi Lynn. Buchele died in a car accident on August 1, 2008 at the age of 88.
The Luther H. Bucheles collection consists of personal and professional correspondence, biographical materia, material related to national and regional student cooperative organizations, as well as the cooperative movement, including surveys, reports, conference material and publications. Also included is material related to Buchele's political activism and interests The collection is organized into two series: Personal and Biographical Material and Cooperatives. The Cooperatives series is divided into three subseries: Student Cooperatives, Cooperative Movement, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Buchele, Luther H., 1920-; Central League of Campus Cooperatives.; Cooperative societies--United States.; Housing cooperatives--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Housing cooperatives--United States.; North American Student Cooperative League.; North American Student Cooperative Organization.; Socialism.; Student housing--United States.; University of Kansas--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.
Genre Terms:
Color slides.; Photographs.
- Personal and Biographical Material
  The Personal and Biographical Material series (1 linear foot, 1935-1990) includes material related to Buchele's time as member of the 4H Club in Kansas, correspondence, material related to his political activism and views, and biographical information. The 4H Club files include material related to and by Luther Buchele's twin brother Wesley F. Buchele, who later taught Agricultural Engineering at Iowa State College (1954-1956), Michigan State University (1956-1963), and Iowa State University (1963-1989). The 1930s-1940s correspondence mostly includes Buchele's exchanges with his mother, brother, and other family members. Later correspondence becomes more professional and reflects Buchele's activities. The bulk of correspondence is dated between 1938 and 1956. Material related to Buchele's political activism, dated mostly 1960s-1970s, includes memoranda, publications, and collected material on various topics, and reflects Buchele's interest in the civil rights movement, labor and unions, peace and Socialism. Also included here is small collection of ephemera related to Buchele's run for the 3rd ward Councilman position in Lawrence, KS in 1950.
  - 4-H Clubs 1935-1938
    - Cooperative Extension Work in Agriculture and Home Economics (Box 1)
    - Essays, published articles, presentations (Box 1)
    - Newsletters (Box 1)
    - Reports by Buchele (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Academic activities and interests 1946, 1949, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Biographical information (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1938-1964, 10 folders (Box 1)
    - 1972-2008 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Identification cards (Box 1)
  - Politics and activism
    - Ann Arbor 1960s Activists Reunion, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Congress of Racial Equality (CORE)
      - 1961-1965 (Box 1)
      - The Picketer, August 1960-February 1961 (Box 1)
    - Councilman campaign 1950 (Lawrence, Kansas) (Box 1)
    - Economic Research in Action Project (Ann Arbor, Mich.) 1960s (Box 1)
    - Labor issues 1965-1980 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings 1960-1990 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Peace 1950-1979 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Socialism
      - Democratic socialism 1970s-1980s (scattered) (Box 1)
      - Socialist Party 1964-1966 (Box 1)
      - Young People's Socialist League 1950-1951 (Box 1)
- Cooperatives
  The Cooperatives series (2 linear feet, 1941-2008) documents Buchele's involvement in the student cooperatives movement and reflects his interest in the cooperative movement.
  - Student Cooperatives
    The Student Cooperative subseries contains material related to local, regional and national student cooperative organizations: the University of Kansas co-ops, CLCC, CLUSA, NASCL, and NASCO. Files include meetings and conference material, surveys, reports, directories, guides and promotional publications, newsletters, historical information, reunion material, and newspaper clippings. Of note is material of the Southeast Asian Workshop on Cooperative and Self-Help Techniques in the University Community that took place in Madras, India in Winter 1958/1959, and was attended by Buchele. Workshop was organized by the World University Service. Files include correspondence and memoranda, reports, programs, publications, photographs, and memorabilia.
    - Central League of Campus Cooperatives (CLCC)
      - Annual conference 1941, 1947-1950, 1958 (Box 2)
      - Financial reports 1948-1949 (Box 2)
      - Newsletter 1949-1951 (Box 2)
      - Promotional material 1947 (Box 2)
    - Circle Pines Center Lift Every Voice and Sing, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Cooperative League of the U.S.A. (CLUSA)
      - Biennial Congress 1950 (Box 2)
      - Publications 1950s (Box 2)
    - Inter-Cooperative Council (ICC), Ann Arbor, Mich. history (Box 2)
    - Midwest Students Cooperatives Conference 1959 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      (bound in 1 volume, with gaps)
      - Campus Co-op Newsletter, 1941-1943 (Box 2)
      - Co-ops on Campus, 1944-1953 (Box 2)
      - Co-ops in Action, 1953-1966 (Box 2)
    - North American Student Cooperative League (NASCL)
      - Bibliographies 1946, 1950 (Box 2)
      - Brief History, 1950 (Box 2)
      - Conferences 1946-1951, 1956, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Guides 1957-1958 (Box 2)
      - News and reports 1951, 1954 (Box 2)
      - Surveys 1949-1957 with gaps (Box 2)
    - North American Student Cooperative Organization (NASCO)
      - Directories 1970-1982 with gaps and 2008 (Box 2)
      - Guides 1987-2002 (scattered) (Box 2)
      - NASCO Institute 2005-2007, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Publications 1970s-1980s (Box 2)
    - Reunions 1976, 1997, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Southeast Asian Workshop on Cooperative and Self-Help Techniques in the University Community 1958-1959, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - University of Kansas
      - Campus Co-op Accounting Manual 1943-1949 (Box 3)
      - History of KU cooperatives (Box 3)
      - Making Do & Getting Through: KU Co-ops, Halls and Houses 1919-1966 by Fred McElhenie (Box 3)
      - Newspaper clippings 1940s (Box 3)
  - Cooperative movement
    Material related to education, research and training constitutes the largest part of the Cooperative Movement subseries. These files include unpublished papers and presentations by Luther Buchele, his wife Joan Buchele, and other authors, study guides, educational and promotional brochures, and workshop material.
    - Education, research and training
      - Bibliographies 1970s (Box 3)
      - Papers and presentations
        - By Joan and Luter Buchele 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
        - By others 1960s-1980s, undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Study guides 1973 (Box 3)
        (?)
      - Workshops 1949-1950 (Box 3)
    - Printed materials
      - Michigan 1940s-1980s (Box 3)
      - Midwest (Box 3)
    - Senior housing cooperatives 1979-2008 (Box 3)
  - Visual materials
    The Visual Materials series includes b&w and color photographs and 35mm color slides depicting group photos from conferences and reunions, as well as images of co-op houses.
    - Photographs 1950s-2000s (Box 3)
    - Slides, 35 mm
      - Circle Pines Center undated, 4 slides (Box 3)
      - CLCC 1949-1987, undated, 9 slides (Box 3)
Related Collections at the Bentley Historical Library
Amy S. Clark collection, 1991-1994. Collection includes oral history interviews.
Inter-Cooperative Council records, 1932-2012 and publications. Finding aid available online
North American Student Cooperative League records, 1936-1977. Finding aid available online
Housing Division (University of Michigan) records, beginning 1923. Finding aid available online